the last thing is but but
how do we know it's a red instruction
remember we need to make our prediction
while we're fetching the instruction so
if this is a return instruction we need
to use the return address stack before
we even determine that it is a return
instruction we cannot just keep pushing
and popping things from the return
address stack
before we know it's a return because for
example if there is an ad and we pop
from the return address stack then it's
not going to work correctly we actually
need to figure out or at least very
accurately predict what's a return
instruction so that we can use the ras
appropriately so the problem is that we
are using the rat while fetching the
instruction it's not been decoded yet so
we don't know it's a return instruction
yet so how do we do it one way is to
just use a very simple predictor that
will be trained on whether the
instruction we're fetching is a red or
not simply train the predictor one way
or the other depending on whether it's a
red or not and then make that predictor
tell us whether to use the return
address stack or not
this would be a very accurate predictor
if at a particular pc we have seen a red
instruction
previously
then it is very likely that if we see
the same pc
we still have a return instruction
so we can use a single bit predictor
very easily here
another approach
is to use a so-called
pre-decoding we will soon see
that the processor really contains a
cache
that stores instructions that have been
fetched from memory and it's fetching
instructions from the cache and only if
the cache doesn't already contain the
instruction it goes through memory so
the pre-decoding
works by when i'm fetching from memory
i decode enough of the instruction
to know that it's a return or not and i
store that information along with the
actual instruction in the cache so
pretty much my memory will for example
have 32-bit instructions
in my cache
i will store 33 bits per instruction 32
bits of the actual instruction and one
bit that tells me whether the
instruction is a return or not
so the idea is that as the instruction
is coming from memory and we put it to
cache
we can be pre-decoding instructions
keeping some additional bits in the
cache about the pre-decoding of the
instructions so that when we fetch we
already know that information
the alternative to this would have been
to just fetch the instructions from
memory to cache as they are and then
every time we fetch we have to figure
out what this instruction is
because it's also more power efficient
to do this once and then fetch the
instruction many times rather than redo
it every single time pre-decoding is a
very popular approach
so predecoding is used for things like
is it a return instruction
is it a branch instruction at all if we
know it's not a branch then we can
completely omit the use of any branch
vectors thus saving a lot of power
if our instructions are of variable
sizes predecoding can also tell us for
example how many bytes this instruction
is long so that we can fetch the next
instruction quickly and not rely on just
decoding the instruction before we can
fetch the next one and so on so there is
a lot of things that modern processors
do in this pre-decoding phase in order
to avoid doing it when we are on the
clock after we have fetched the
instruction